Guide to the Saul Mills Papers WAG.075
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Saul Mills Papers
1935-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mills, Saul, 1910-1988
Mills, Agnes Karlin
Mills-Thysen, Marghe
WAG.075
4.25 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 8 folders
Saul Mills was a union activist, PR representative and journalist born in New York in 1910. Between 1927 and 1936, Mills worked in varying capacities with a number of newspapers, including The New York Daily News, The Brooklyn Daily Eagle, The Brooklyn Standard Union and The City News Association. Mills' newspaper experience and his association with the noted newspaper columnist Heywood Broun gave rise to Mills' involvement in the labor movement. In 1934, he became a charter member of Broun's Newspaper Guild which led to Mills being dismissed from The Eagle. Between 1936 and 1940, Mills worked as a public relations representative for CIO and AFL affiliated unions and later went into private PR practice. The collection includes: Mills' personal correspondence, Greater New York CIO Council administrative records, photographs and ephemera that document various aspects of Mills' work and life.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Agnes Karlin Mills, 1990. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1990.015, 1990.016, and NPA 2003.071.
A second donation was made by Marghe Mills-Thysen, 2008. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2018.027 and NPA 2008.007.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Saul Mills (born Solomon Schneidmill) was born to Isidore and Celia Schneidmill in Manhattan, New York, on May 10, 1910. After his mother's death, Mills, age five, entered an orphans' home. Just prior to the completion of his elementary school education, Mills left the orphanage and returned to his father's home, which by then provided for nine other children. While attending high school Mills worked full time as a copy boy, first for the Associated Press, and later the United Press. Mills left high school during his senior year after being offered an opportunity for advancement working as a wire-filler at United Press.
Between 1927 and 1936 Mills worked in varying capacities on a wide range of newspapers which included The Long Island Press, The New York Daily News, The Brooklyn Daily Eagle, The Brooklyn Standard Union, The Monmouth County Record(NJ), and The City News Association. Mills' experiences while employed at the Press and at the Eagle provided the impetus toward full time union work. Mills' association with the noted newspaper columnist, Heywood Broun, further shaped his burgeoning interest int he labor movement. When in December 1934 Broun called for the establishment of the Newspaper Guild, Mills, then a reporter on the Eagle, became one of its charter members. Mills' subsequent union activity led to his dismissal at the Eagle. It was at this time that Mills came into contact with left-wing and Communist activists within the labor movement.
1936 was a pivotal year for Mills. He left the newspaper business, married the artist Agnes Karlin, and began his association with the Congress of Industrial Organizations. Between 1936 and 1940 Mills worked - often without pay - as a public relations representative for many burgeoning trade unions, both CIO and AFL affiliated. When, in 1940, the National CIO established the Greater NY CIO Council, Mills, at the request of John L. Lewis and Allan Haywood, assumed the position of Secretary-Treasurer, a post he was to keep for the duration of the Council's existence.
With the United Sates' entry into World War II, Mills participated in numerous CIO Council war relief programs, was appointed by President Roosevelt to the Greater New York Regional War Manpower Commission, and as an advisor to the New York Regional War Labor Board; the War Production Board; and the Office of Price Administration. He was Secretary of NY-CIO War Chest, and Co-Chairman of the Joint AFL-CIO Industry Relations Committee. In the early 1940s Mills was elected, but served only for a short time, as vice chairman of the American Labor Party. In June 1942 Mills participated in organizing the Central Park meeting, "Labor Salutes the Armed Forces," one of the largest gatherings of its time; he later supported the Communist-affiliated "Open the Second Front," movement.
Mills contributed to the creation of what later became the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (HIP). In 1946, he served as vice-president and chairman of HIP's administrative committee, and later became a member of the HIP Board of Incorporators. From 1943 to 1948 Mills served on the Board of Directors of Associated Hospital Service (New York Blue Cross).
With the dissolution of the CIO Council in 1948, Mills entered private business. Between 1948 and 1950 he was an associate member and account executive with Goldby, Byrne, and Associates, Inc., a business involved in fund-raising and public relations for health and educational institutions. Mills later had his own public relations form, Mills Agency, which specialized in direct-marketing for mail-order and insurance companies. In 1949, as a representative of the Seacoast Export Corporation, Mills embarked on a six-month trip to China. After his return home, Mills entered into a business arrangement with the American-Chinese Export Corporation (owned by Frederick Vanderbilt Field). When his business enterprises in the Orient were curtailed by the Korean War, Mills returned to fund raising and the health insurance field. From 1950 to 1952, Mills directed capital fund campaigns for the Hebew Home and Hospital for the Aged in Brooklyn, and the citizen-sponsored Bayonne Community Center in Bayonne, New Jersey.
In 1956 Mills was subpoenaed to appear before a subcommittee of the U.S. Senate Internal Security Committee. He was questioned regarding his activities while an executive member of the Greater NY CIO Council, his association with the Chinese Communists (U.N. delegates) in 1945, his 1949 trip to China, and his business affiliations with Communist sympathizer, Frederick Vanderbilt Field. Mills testified that he was not a Communist Party member, nor had he ever been, and that his relationship was as a representative of CIO Council. His 1949 trip to China was based on private financial interests, as was his business association with Frederick Fields and the American-Chinese Export Corporation.
Between 1953 and 1963, Mills was Director of Development for the Long Island Jewish Hospital. In 1963 Mills became a partner with E.D. Rosenfeld Associates, Inc., a hospital and health services consulting firm. His work with the Human Resources Center during the 1960s resulted in the opening of a school for physically-challenged children. During the mid-1960s Mills participated in fund raising for two organizations associated with Martin Luther King: The Voter Education Fund, sponsored by the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, and the Gandhi Society fir Human Rights. Throughout his life, Mills was actively involved in various political causes. Mills died on 26 November 1988 after a long illness. His obituary recorded his request that in lieu of flowers, contributions be made to Amnesty International.
Brief History of the Greater NY CIO Council:
The Greater New York CIO Council was the central body of the CIO unions in the greater New York area. Established by the national Congress of Industrial Organizations in July 1940, the Council represented, during its eight year history, approximately 200 CIO local unions (400,000 workers). The Council's Digest Minutes reflect a history of commitment to a broad range of activities and interests. The Council was active in price and rent control, combating racial discrimination, and campaigning for a raise in workers' wages. The Council, as a conduit for labor solidarity, assisted union organizing drives through the provision of funds, and contributed to union strikes by swelling the numbers behind the picket lines. During 1941 the Council was active in supporting the department store strikes, such as those at Gimbel's, and Macy's. It supported the Transport Workers Union bus negotiations, launched a legislative campaign against the Dies Committee, participated in the Madison Square park demonstration to stop Hitler, and organized a joint union campaign for War Aid. In 1942 the Council supported President Roosevelt's Seven-Point Anti-Inflation Program, broadcasted "Win the War Programs", and participated in the "New York at War" parade. The Council in tandem with the American Labor Party, with which it was affiliated, played a major role in the reelection of Franklin D. Roosevelt to a fourth term.
With the United States' entry into the war, the Council contributed toward Victory efforts by mobilizing its affiliate union members in a variety of activities, such as blood donor drives and civil defense projects. To ensure the production of war goods during this period, the Council supported Roosevelt's "no-strike" pledge.
After the war, the Council addressed the problem of returning veterans, and post-war concerns of housing and mass employment. It continued its campaign for health insurance benefits, fought the Taft-Hartley bills and other anti-labor legislation. Although the Council organizationally never endorsed Henry A. Wallace for president, the Council claimed that a majority of its delegates favored his candidacy, supported the Progressive Party, and opposed the Marshall Plan. In deference to national CIO policy, the Council tabled action on all three issues; but their position regarding these issues remained clear. It was the Council's unofficial position on these last three issues, plus its advocacy of freedom of expression for political differences, which brought the Council into conflict with the State CIO Council's reiteration of national CIO Political Action Committee's resolutions regarding opposition to a third party in 1948 and support of the Marshall Plan.
Cold War reaction to left and Communist activists within the labor movement significantly modified the national CIO leadership's earlier tolerance toward diverse political philosophies. Political differences polarized when John Brophy, Director of State CIO Councils, issued his dictum (the Brophy letter) regarding the adoption of national CIO policy by all city councils (of which the Greater NY CIO Council was one). The Council interpreted the demands for political conformity as an attack on the principles of trade union democracy. The ensuing internecine quarrels between the state CIO leadership and the Council led directly to the latter's dissolution.
On September 27, 1948, a committee of the New York State CIO Council requested that the Greater New York CIO Council's charter be revoked. Among the charges levied against the Council were: violation of CIO constitution and its rules, and, "through disruptive and irresponsible actions [promoting] disunity and discord within the ranks of CIO unions." Further, the Council was charged with "aiding and abetting...enemies of labor" and publicly "slandering, vilifying and libeling the CIO" More specific charges included the Council's opposition to increases in New York City's subway fare and its interference with the transport Workers Union's efforts to achieve higher wages. Moreover, it was charged, that the Council had engaged in political activities which were contrary to New York State CIO PAC programs. The formal complaint, addressed to National CIO President Phillip Murray, was signed by State CIO Council members Michael Quill (former Council president), Joseph Curran, Norma Naughton, Jack Rubinstein, and Jack Altman.
In response to the charges, Murray appointed a three-man investigatory committee which conducted closed hearings at CIO national headquarters on October 14 and 15, 1948. Although the committee found the Council guilty of the charges, its recommendations were not made public until the following month, when at the Annual CIO Convention the findings of the hearing committee were affirmed by a vote of 38 to 5; Louis Hollander, president of the New York State CIO Council, was instructed to assume administrative responsibility for the Council. The executive officers of the Council, James Durkin and Saul Mills, accepted the verdict in the interest of CIO unity.
Sources:
New Yorkers at Work(oral history interviews and study guides), Wagner Labor Archives.
Foster, James Caldwell. The Union Politic: The CIO Political Action Committee.(University of Missouri Press, 1975).
Foner, Henry. "Saul Mills and the Greater New York Industrial Union Council, CIO." Labor History, Vol. 31, No. 3, 1990.
Scope and Contents
The Saul Mills Papers contain correspondence, Greater New York CIO Council administrative records, and documentation of Mills' work in health insurance, advertising, and political fund raising. The collection, which spans the years 1933-1989, has been arranged in the following series: I. Biographical Information and Personal Correspondence (1930s-1989); II. CIO and Other Labor/Political Activities (1933-1965); III. Saul Mills: Business Ventures (1949-1981); IV. Photographs, Drawings, Artifacts and Ephemera.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 4 series: I. Biographical Information and Personal Correspondence (1930s-1989); II. CIO and Other Labor/Political Activities (1933-1965); III. Saul Mills: Business Ventures (1949-1981); IV. Photographs, Drawings, Artifacts and Ephemera.
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
NYC Central Labor Council Collection (including the Greater NYCIO Council, Council Minutes/Digest, 1940-1948 and the Greater NY CIO Council, Executive Board Minutes, 1944-1948). Records of the Transport Workers Union of America. Oral history interview with Saul Mills, in the New Yorkers at Work series, Wagner Labor Archives Oral History Collections.
Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; New York (N.Y.).; Collective bargaining -- New York (State) -- New York.; Communists -- United States.; Radicals -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor disputes -- New York (State) -- New York.; Oral histories (literary works); Records (documents); Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reports.; Insurance, Health |z New York (State) |z New York.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Veterans.; China -- Politics and government.; Public health -- United States.; Newspaper employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Newspaper employees |z New York (State); Labor movement -- United States.; Communists |z China.; Anti-communist movements -- United States.; Public relations consultants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Race discrimination -- New York (State) -- New York.; Rent control -- New York (State) -- New York; Wages |z New York (State) |z New York.; Blue Cross of Greater New York; Broun, Heywood, 1888-1939; Goldby, Byrne, and Associates, inc.; Seacoast Export Corporation; Mills Agency; Mills, Saul, 1910-1988; Greater New York Industrial Union Council; American Labor Party; Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969; Mills, Agnes Karlin; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Newspaper Guild; Field, Frederick V. (Frederick Vanderbilt), 1905-2000; Haywood, Allan S., 1888-1953; AFL-CIO; Transport Workers Union of America; Gandhi Society for Human Rights; Quill, Mike, 1905-1966; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws; American-Chinese Export Corporation; Voter Education Project (Southern Regional Council); Long Island Jewish Hospital; Mills, Agnes Karlin; Mills-Thysen, Marghe
- Series I: Biographical Information and Personal Correspondence, 1930s-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Biographical Information and Personal Correspondence (1930s-1989) contains biographical information, family correspondence, diaries and an oral history interview done just after Mills' retirement in 1981. The correspondence in this series is particularly rich in references to Mills' union activity during the 1930s. Correspondence from the 1940s refers to general Council business and war-related activities. Of particular interest is correspondence from Mills to his wife during the Annual CIO Convention in November 1948, including his observations regarding the Expulsion Hearings and the subsequent action taken during the Convention with respect to the Council. The series also contains correspondence from Mills' travels through China during 1949.
  - Biographical Information I, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Information II, 1950-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: General, 1949-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Saul Mills/Agnes Karlin, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: S.M. to Agnes Mills, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: S.M. to Agnes Mills, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Agnes Mills to S.M., undated, 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from China: S.M. to Family, 1949-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1945, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: CIO and Other Labor/Political Activities, 1933-1965
  Series II: CIO and Other Labor/Political Activities (1933-1965) is divided into two subseries. Subseries A: CIO Union and PAC Activities reflects a wide range of Council activity, in particular, Mills' interest, as a union representative, in health insurance. The series documents the emerging conflicts between national CIO policy and Council actions. The collection contains clippings which record the controversy over the Brophy letter and the Council's alleged interference with international unions' strike activities. Of special interest, too, are the Council's Executive Board Minutes, and the Council's Digest Minutes. Both sets of minutes are incomplete. Subseries B: Expulsion hearings contains a substantial amount of material documenting both the Council's defense and complains' charges. Besides the Hearing Committee's findings, and other official CIO documents, the subseries contains a virulent rebuttal by Michael Quill (one of the complainants), and a lengthy statement of defense by the Council.
  - Subseries A: General Files, 1933-1965
    - Brophy Letter, undated, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - CIO Action Guide, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - CIO Delegation to USSR, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Council Digests, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - CIO National Convention, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - CIO Political Action Committee, undated, 1944, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - CIO Veterans Activities, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Commission of the World Federation of Trade Unions to Investigate Conditions in Germany, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Financial Data, undated, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Greater NY CIO Council, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Greater NY CIO Council, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Greater NY CIO Council, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Greater NY CIO Council, Jan 1948-Aug 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Greater NY CIO Council, Sep 1948-Nov 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Greater NY CIO Council: Constitution and Rules, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Greater NY CIO Council: Executive Board Minutes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Greater NY CIO Council: Reports, 1940, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, 1948-1949, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Interference Issue (5c fare), undated, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Martin Luther King/Voter Educational Fund, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - National CIO War Relief Committee, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Guild, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper Guild, 1945, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - New York Labor War Chest, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Rental Problems, 1944-1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Speeches (Saul Mills), 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Union Activities: Miscellaneous, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - US Naval Training Center, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Subseries B: Greater NY CIO Council Expulsion Hearings, 1948-1956
    - Charges against Greater New York CIO Council, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Executive Board Committee Findings, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Expulsion Clippings, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hearings: Bound Copy, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hearings: Committee Exhibits 1-16, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Hearings: Exhibits "A"-"K", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hearings: Exhibits "L"-"V", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hearings: Durkin, J. Exhibits 1-3; Young, R. Exhibits 1-2, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Hearings: Mills, S. Exhibits 1-7, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hearings: Quill, M. J. Exhibit 1; McGrath P. Exhibits 1-2, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hearings: Wolchok, S. Exhibits 1-22; Brothy, J. Exhibit 1, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hearings: Statements and Rebuttals, Oct 1948-Nov 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Press Releases, Jan 5, 1948-Mar 30, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases, Apr 3, 1948-May 27, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases, Jun 3, 1948-Oct 18, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Report: "Hearings in Washington", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Testimony before US Senate Subcommittee for Internal Security, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series III: Saul Mills: Business Ventures and Public Concerns, 1949-1981
  Series III: Saul Mills: Business Ventures (1949-1981) pertains to Mills' life after the dissolution of the Council. This series documents Mills' observations of China in 1949 during his travels there as a representative of an export-import company, as well as his continued interest in public health and group insurance plans; his work with the Gandhi Society for Human Rights, the Hebrew National Orphan Home and Hebrew Home for the Aged, the Rehabilitation Institute, and numerous private business enterprises.
  - China, Business Correspondence, 1949, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - China, Cablegrams, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - China Log, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - China: Notes, Speeches, Memorandum, undated, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - China, Trade with, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Gandhi Society for Human Rights, undated, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Health Care: General, 1951-1953 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Health Dental Insurance, Inc., undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Health: Long Island Jewish Hospital, 1954-1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Hebrew Home for the Aged (Brooklyn), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Human Resource Center, undated, 1963-1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Human Resource Center, 1968-1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Maccabiah Games ouvenir Book, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Jerusalem Convention Center Association, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., Jan 1981-Aug 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., Sep 1981-Dec 1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., Jan 1982-Apr 1982 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., May 1982-Dec 1982 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1983 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1984 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Mills Agency, Inc., 1985, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Orphan Home, Hebrew National, undated, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Planeteria, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Rehabilitation Institute, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - See-Well, Inc., undated, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 20)